Guide to the Jacques Barzun Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series II: 1976 Gift
  - Recommendations -- friends & students:
    - General (Box 137)
    - A-F (Box 137)
    - G -- M (Box 138)
    - N-Z (Box 139)
  - Speeches:
    - 1933-1957 (Box 140)
    - 1957-1960 (Box 141)
    - 1961-1964 (Box 142)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 143)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 144)
    - 1969-1971 (Box 145)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 146)
  - Tributes to various people, 1940-1975 (Box 146)
  - Columbia University:
    - Advising (as Dean), 1963-1968 (Box 147)
    - Advisory Commission on the arts, 1962 (Box 147)
    - Alumni program (national), 1964-1975 (Box 147)
    - Annual report, 1956-1970 (Box 147)
    - Cabinet meetings -- minutes, 1962-1964 (Box 147)
    - Cabinet meetings -- minutes, 1964-1967 (Box 148)
    - Campus invitations, 1965-1974 (Box 148)
    - Campus lectures, 1965-1967 (Box 148)
    - C.U. Brochure, 1961-1963 (Box 148)
    - C.U. Panorama (Box 148)
    - Dean of Faculties -- general correspondence, 1963-1967 (Box 148)
    - Dear of Faculties -- office (index to files) (Box 148)
    - Deans & Provosts, 1958-1968 (Box 149)
    - Development -- General problem for future deliberation, 1965-1966 (Box 149)
    - Development -- Master Planning Committee, 1966-1969 (Box 149)
    - Development--Master Planning Committee: Agenda, 1966 (Box 149)
    - Development--Master Planning Committee: Barzun report, 1966-1967 (Box 149)
    - Development--Master Planning Committee: Space (classrooms, etc.) (Box 149)
    - Fund raising campaign, 1965-1969 (Box 150)
    - Fund raising campaign:
      - Arden House notes, 1966 (Box 150)
      - Faculty salaries, 1966 (Box 150)
      - Ford Foundation presentations, 1966 (Box 150)
      - "History of schools", 1966 (Box 150)
      - Kersting, Brown & Co., 1966 (Box 150)
      - New York City & Columbia, 1966 (Box 150)
      - Other fund drives, 1966 (Box 150)
      - Overall figures, expenditures, 1965-1966 (Box 150)
      - Proposed goals, 1966 (Box 150)
    - Graduate Students by Hans Rosenhaupt, 1957-1969 (Box 151)
    - History project for city schools (Box 151)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 151)
    - National Committee on the Humanities, 1956-1968 (Box 151)
    - Odyssey review, 1962 (Box 151)
    - Official statements, 1961-1969 (Box 151)
    - Old Dominion Foundation, Inc., 1956-1959 (Box 151)
    - Radiation seminar (Kusch), 1960-1961 (Box 151)
    - "Records of Civilization", 1962-1964 (Box 151)
    - Special cases, 1967-1975 (Box 151)
    - Special cases -- A. Levitt, 1967-1970 (Box 151)
    - Special cases -- S.J. Spingara, 1969-1971 (Box 151)
    - Special cases -- H. Wang, 1957-1967 (Box 151)
    - Statutes, 1966-1968 (Box 151)
    - Suggestions, 1955-1967 (Box 151)
    - University affairs, 1957-1968 (Box 152)
    - University on the Heights, 1967-1970 (Box 152)
    - University Professor -- Office procedures book (Box 152)
    - University -- special projects, 1959-1967 (Box 152)
    - University study (T. Caplow), 1955-1956 (Box 152)
  - Who’s who file: general & A-J (clippings, pictures, obituaries, etc) (Box 153)
  - Who’s who file: K-Z (Box 154)
  - Arts and letters:
    - American Council of Learned Societies -- Committee on musicology, 1955-1959 (Box 155)
    - Arts and letters -- printed miscellaneous, 1967-1975 (Box 155)
    - Columbia University: The arts at Columbia University, 1958-1970 (Box 155)
    - Music: General correspondence, 1950-1974 (Box 156)
    - The Music Guild, 1961-1963 (Box 156)
    - National Institute of Arts and Letters -- J.B. President, 1972-1973 (Box 156)
    - National Institute of Arts and Letters -- 75th Anniversary speech by J.B., 16 May (Box 157)
    - The RCA Victor Society of Great Music, 1957-1961 (Box 157)
    - Reader’s Digest Music, Inc., 1961-1964 (Box 157)
    - The Serious Music Society, Inc. 1964-1966 (Box 157)
    - Darwin, Marx, and Wagner. Correspondence, 1935-1972 (Box 157)
  - Berlioz and the Romantic Century. Printed pages (Box 158)
  - Classical, Romantic, and Modern. Preface to 2nd edition and epilogue, 1960 (Box 158)
  - Follett’s Modern American Usage. Advance copies list (Box 158)
  - Introduction to Evening With the Orchestra by Berlioz. Book dummy, 1956 (Box 158)
  - Romanticism and the Moden Ego. Excerpts (Box 158)
  - Science. Advance copies list, 1964 (Box 158)
  - The Selected Writings of John Jay Chapman. Introduction (Box 158)
  - Teacher in America. Excerpt, 1945 (Box 158)
  - Announcements, press releases, etc. -- printed misc. (Box 158)
  - DuVall, Jack. "Barzun: a Brief Portrait in Depth Historiography", 1967 (Box 158)
  - Krystal, A. "Oskisis." (Box 158)
  - Little, Brown and Company -- "Books by Jacques Barzun", 1945 (Box 158)
  - Symposium, Exploration of the ways, means and values of museum communication with the viewing public. Sponsored by The Museum of the City of New York and The New York State Council on the Arts, October 1967 (Box 158)
  - Articles by Barzun (manuscripts) -- no date (Box 159)
  - Articles by Barzun, 1924-1966 (Box 160)
  - Manuscripts by others (edited by Barzun): (Cass, Myrtle Margaret, trans Cardan:De Subtilitate. Books 2-7. Endore, Guy, trans. Principles of philosophy by Rene Descartes. Gifler, Bernard. Goetz von Berlichingen, 1930 (Box 161)
  - Columbia University:
    - Trilling-Barzun Seminars. (Class books), 1928-1965 (Box 162)
    - Barzun Class books
  - Notes & clippings file:
    - Criticism, 1959-1960 (Box 163)
    - Education -- C.U., 1959-1960 (Box 163)
    - France, 1959 (Box 163)
    - History -- book notices, 1934-1947 (Box 163)
    - History -- Government -- Law, 1959 (Box 163)
    - Intellect, 1959-1960 (Box 163)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1947-1952 (Box 163)
    - Modernism, 1959-1960 (Box 163)
    - Music, 1960 (Box 163)
    - Persons (and obituaries), 1935-1971 (Box 163)
    - Philosophy, 1935-1947 (Box 163)
    - Religion, 1942-1946 (Box 163)
    - Sea power: 3000 years of naval warfare, 1944-1946 (Box 163)
    - Ships, naval history, etc., 1942-1955 (Box 163)
    - Translations & words, 1957-1959 (Box 163)
    - War and peace, 1945-1951 (Box 163)
  - Papers about Barzun:
    - Baird, Newton: "Aristotle’s operative, or, the case of the classic Barzun", 1975 (Box 163a)
    - DuVall, "Jack: Barzun: a brief portrait in depth historiography", 1967 (Box 163a)
    - Goldman, Richard Franke: "Jacques Barzun", 1972 (Box 163a)
    - Maffett, I. Lamar, Jr.: "Jacques Barzun on the decay and reformation of modern higher education in America:, 1971 (Box 163a)
    - Poorman, Richard O.: "Jacques Barzun: critic of American schools", 1960 (Box 162a)
  - Personal:
    - Bell, Charles G: Poems, 1953 (Box 164)
    - Berlioz library -- J.B.’s bookplates (Box 164)
    - Boniface, William: Poems, 1965 (Box 164)
    - Clough, Rosa Trillo: Modern Italian Poems (Box 164)
    - Davison, Peter: The poems of cruelty, 1966 (Box 164)
    - Diaries, 1933-1934 (Box 164)
    - Flute (Box 204)
    - Fournier, Pierre S.: Ca (Box 164)
    - Lists and Miscellaneous (Box 164)
    - Lowell, F.E. -- watercolors (list) (Box 164)
    - New York Public Library, 1969 (Box 164)
    - Ration books, 1942 (Box 164)
    - Record library--lists (Box 164)
    - Recordings--blurbs (Box 164)
    - Stout, Rex, 1965-1974 (Box 164)
    - Theater -- programs & memorabilia (Box 164)
    - Miscellaneous -- Matthiessen, Conrad Henry. Correspondence found in an old file, 1895-1926 (Box 164)
  - "Article file" -- "Master copies": Periodicals (most have contributions by Barzun) (Box 165-176)
  - Photographs (Box 177)
  - Home movies (Box 177)
  - Pictures, illustrations, postcards, etc. (Box 177)
  - Books by Barzun (Box 178)
  - Books edited or translated by' Barzun (Box 179)
  - Books with introductions by Barzun (Box 180-181)
  - Books with contributions by Barzun (Box 182-186)
  - Books autographed or inscribed to Barzun (Box 187-191)
  - Books with Barzun’s note & printed misc. (Box 192)
  - Volumes of pamphlets (some by Barzun) (Box 193)
  - Offprints and reprints autographed and inscribed to Barzun (Box 194)
  - Periodicals autographed or inscribed to Barzun (Box 195)
  - Tape recordings: See attached list, p. 15 (Box 196-197)
  - Microfilms: See attached list, p. 16 (Box 198-199)
  - Modern music scores: See attached list, p. 17 (Box 200)
  - American Friends of Cambridge University, Inc., 1970-73 (Box 201)
  - Art ---advising, 1960-61 (Box 201)
  - Barzun--biographical & bibliographical notes (Box 201)
  - Council for Basic Education, 1973-75 (Box 201)
  - Critic -- general, 1968-73 (Box 201)
  - Criticism--other authors, 1966-75 (Box 201)
  - Fifty classics of crime fiction 1900-1950. By Barzun and Wendell H. Taylor. Drafts (Box 202)
  - Literary matters pending, 1968-75 (Box 202)
  - Open Court, 1968-72 (Box 202)
  - Peabody Institute, 1973-74 (Box 202)
  - Simple & direct: a rhetoric for authors. Notes (Box 202)
  - Simple & direct: a rhetoric for authors. Notes & clippings (Box 203)
  - French metronome (Box 204)
  - Wooden flute & small flute (Box 204)
  - Books by and about Barzun (Box 205)
  - Grant, Henry Adams: Charcoal portrait of Jacques Barzun, 1926 (Box Oversize)
  - Thayer, Polly: Charcoal portrait of Jacques Barzun, 1944 (Box Oversize)
- Series III: 1977 Gift
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1957-71 (Box 206)
  - American Historical Association, 1961-77 (Box 206)
  - The American Scholar, 1973-77 (Box 206)
  - The Association for American Achievements, Inc. 1970-76 (Box 206)
  - The Baker Street Irregulars, 1954-76 (Box 206)
  - Burke and Hare: the resurrection men, 1972-75 (Box 206)
  - A Catalogue of Crime, 1973-74 (Box 206)
  - Churchill College, Cambridge, 1961-77 (Box 206)
  - C.U. University Professor, 1964-77 (Box 207)
  - Congratulatory letters on retirement, 1975 (Box 207)
  - Contracts, 1949-73 (Box 207)
  - Council for Basic Education, 1975-76 (Box 208)
  - The delights of detection, 1969-72 (Box 208)
  - Detective fiction --correspondence, 1973-76 (Box 208)
  - The Educational Forum, 1969-73 (Box 208)
  - 1170 Fifth Avenue Corp. " Board, 1975-77 (Box 208)
  - Friends of the Columbia Libraries, 1973-77 (Box 208)
  - Language, 1952-74 (Box 208)
  - Macmillan, Inc. Board, 1976 (Box 209)
  - Mellon Lectures-National Gallery of Art (Box 209)
  - Members & sponsors -- associations, 1967-75 (Box 209)
  - National Book Awards, 1976-77 (Box 209)
  - Simple & direct. Correspondence, 1974-76 (Box 209)
  - Town Hall Board, 1971-75 (Box 209)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun, 1971-77 (Box 210)
- Series IV: 1978 Gift
  - Advice to authors 1974-78 (Box 211)
  - Advice to publishers 1965-76 (Box 211)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters-National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1974-76 (Box 211)
  - American Arbitration Association: The Lyle Stuart, Inc. vs. Joan Garrity. Sensuous Woman. (l), 1977 (Box 212)
  - American Arbitration Association, The Lyle Stuart Inc. vs. Joan Garrity. Sensuous Woman, (2) 1977 (Box 213)
  - Clark, M.L.: Lincoln essay by Barzun, 1974-77 (Box 214)
  - Council for Basic Education, 1977 (Box 214)
  - Council for Basic Education --Commission on writiing form letters (J.B. as Provost of Columbia University), 1974-75 (Box 214)
  - Lectures; accepted, 1974-76 (Box 215)
  - Lectures: declined, 1964-76 (Box 215)
  - Peabody Institute, Baltimore, 1975-76 (Box 215)
  - Permissions, 1955-75 (Box 215)
  - The University College at Buckingham [U.K.], 1974-76 (Box 215)
  - Books with contributions by Barzun (Box 216)
  - Books with contributions by Barzun (Box 217)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun (Box 217)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun (Box 218)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun (Box 219)
  - J. Barzun's Appointment Books 1956-1975 (Gift of Virginia Xanthos, 1975) (Box 220)
  - Papers of Sir James Fitzjames Stephens: xeroxes & microfilms. (Gift-Virginia Xanthos, 1975) (Box 221)
  - Family correspondence. 8 correspondence files, 1 tin box and 2 small cartons
    [Restricted]
  - Classic, Romantic and Modern. Book jacket design. (Box OVERSIZE)
  - Harry Partsch-Musical works. Portfolio (Box OVERSIZE)
  - Edgar Varese-Photograph (Box OVERSIZE)
  - Scrapbook of reproductions of Renaissance paintings. (Box OVERSIZE)
  - Grant, Henry Adams: Charcoal portrait of Jacques Barzun, 1926 (Box OVERSIZE)
  - Thayer, Polly: Charcoal portrait of Jacques Barzun, 1944 (Box OVERSIZE)
- Series V: 1979 Gift
  - Académie Delphinale, 1952-75 (Box 222)
  - Advice to authors, 1977 (Box 222)
  - Advice to publishers, 1977 (Box 222)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1969-75 (Box 222)
  - American Friends of Cambridge University, 1974-77 (Box 222)
  - Articles declined, 1956-77 (Box 222)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1977 (Box 222)
  - The Author Guild, Inc., 1972-76 (Box 222)
  - Biographical information on J.B., 1960-78 (Box 223)
  - Commission on Writing, 1977-78 (Box 223)
  - Council for Basic Education, 1978 (Box 223)
  - Critics -- General, 1975-77 (Box 223)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1969-79 (Box 223)
  - Lectures accepted, 1976-78 (Box 224)
  - Lectures declined, 1967-77 (Box 224)
  - New York Society Library, 1969-77 (Box 224)
  - Peabody Institute, Baltimore, 1977-78 (Box 224)
  - The Royal Society of Arts, London, 1960-76 (Box 224)
  - Society for Social Studies of Science, 1976 (Box 224)
  - Printed announcements, programs, etc., 1978-79 (Box 225)
  - Books by Barzun. inscribed to him, etc. (Box 226)
  - Books by Barzun, inscribed to him, etc. (Box 227)
- Series VI: 1980 Gift
  - Correspondence, 1972-76 (Box 228)
  - American Friends of Cambridge University, 1977-79 (Box 228)
  - Articles accepted, 1976-77 (Box 228)
  - Lectures accepted, 1978-79 (Box 228)
  - Lectures declined, 1977-78 (Box 228)
  - Library gifts & other contributions, 1971-75 (Box 228)
  - Miscellaneous invitations, 1976-78 (Box 228)
  - The New York Society Library, 1978-79 (Box 228)
  - Open Court Publications, 1973-77 (Box 228)
  - Publicity (duplicates only) (Box 229)
  - Manuscripts edited by Jacques Barzun:
    - Keck:How to take care of your pictures. (Box 229)
    - Steeves:History of feminism. (Box 229)
    - Tibbetts: What's happening to American EnglishÀ (Box 229)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun, with his contributions, etc. (Box 230)
  - Books with Barzun' s notes, etc., & misc. printed items (Box 231)
- Series VII: 1981 Gift
  - Advice to authors, 1978-80 (Box 232)
  - Advice to publishers, 1978 (Box 232)
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1979-80 (Box 232)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1976-1980 (Box 232)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1962-1979 (Box 232)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1957 1979 (Box 232)
  - American Friends of Cambridge University, 1979 (Box 232)
  - Articles accepted, 1978 (Box 232)
  - The Century Association, 1972-1978 (Box 233)
  - Council for Basic Education, 1979 (Box 233)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1979 (Box 233)
  - Fifty classics of crime fiction, 1900-1950 1914-1978 (Box 233)
  - Great books of the 20th Century, 1977-1978 (Box 233)
  - Institute for Philosophic Research, 1968-1978 (Box 233)
  - Lectures accepted, 1978-1980 (Box 233)
  - Lectures declined, 1979 (Box 234)
  - Peabody Institute, 1979-1980 (Box 234)
  - Personal notices, 1968-1980 (Box 234)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun or with his notes (Box 235)
  - Music scores: See attached list, p. 17. (Box 236)
- Series VIII: December 1981 Gift
  - Letters: family-"Letters to and about M.L.B., 1978-1979 (Shelved with other family letters) (Box 237)
    [RESTRICTED]
  - Letters: friends--Wendell H. Taylor, 1972-1983 (Continues series from Box 106; Continues in Box 278) (Box 238)
  - Advise to authors, 1979 (Box 239)
  - Appeals to J.B. as critic -- general, 1978 (Box 239)
  - Black Papers (Manchester, UK), 1972-1977 (Box 239)
  - American Arbitration Association, 1978-1980 (Box 239)
  - Chestnut Hill College (Philadelphia), 1979 (Box 239)
  - Comments on articles, 1974-1977 (Box 239)
  - Comments on lectures, 1972-1975 (Box 239)
  - Council tor Basic Education-Board of Directors, 1980 (Box 239)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica-Board of Editors, 1980 (Box 239)
  - The New York Society Library, 1979 (Box 239)
  - Open Court Publications, 1978 (Box 239)
  - Peabody Institute (Baltimore)-Board of Trustees, 1980 (Box 239)
  - The Times Literary Supplement, 1976-1978 (Box 239)
  - Word Watchers, 1977-1980 (Box 239)
  - Books by, edited by, with contributions by, or mentioning Jacques Barzun (Box 240)
  - Books inscribed to Jacques Barzun (Box 241)
  - Printed miscel1any (Box 241)
  - 3 drawings by Arrigo Lora-Totino (Box Oversize)
- Series IX: 1983 Gift
  - Advice to authors, 1980 (Box 242)
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1977 (Box 242)
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1978 (Box 242)
  - American Academy" and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1980 (Box 242)
  - American Friends of Cambridge University, 1980 (Box 242)
  - Articles accepted, 1972-76 (Box 244)
  - The Authors Guild, Inc., 1976-80 (Box 244)
  - The Athenaeum (London), 1962-76 (Box 244)
  - The Century Association, 1970-79 (Box 244)
  - Columbia administrative correspondence, 1975-79 (Box 244)
  - Columbia personal correspondence, 1973-78 (Box 244)
  - Columbia Professor Emeritus, 1973-79 (Box 244)
  - Council for Basic Education, 1981 (Box 245)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1980-81 (Box 245)
  - Institute tor Philosophical Research, 1979-80 (Box 245)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society, 1961-77 (Box 245)
  - Members & sponsors, 1975-78 (Box 245)
  - The New York Society Library, 1980 (Box 245)
  - Peabody Institute...Conservatory of Music, Baltimore, 1981 (Box 245)
  - Personal: A-J, 1958-78 (Box 246)
  - Personal: K --Z, 1958-78 (Box 247)
  - The Society of American Historians, Inc., 1954-80 (Box 248)
  - Lionel and Diana Trilling, 1975-78 (Box 248)
  - Lionel Trilling Seminars, 1976-80 (Box 248)
  - Manuscripts, proofs, & photocopies sent to JB (Box 248)
  - Books by Barzun (Box 249)
  - Books with Barzun's notes (Box 250)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun (Box 251-253)
- Series X: April 1983 Gift
  - Notes & printed materials on William James (Box 254)
  - Adler, Mortimer J.: "Paideia" typescript corrected by Barzun, 1982-1983 (Box 255)
  - Photographs, 1944-78 (Box 255)
  - Books & pamphlets inscribed to Barzun (Box 255)
  - Books by Barzun or with his contributions (Box 256)
  - Metropolitan Opera program facsimi1e, 16 November 1908 (Box Oversize)
- Series XI: July 1983 Gift
  - Notes & printed materials on William James (including a proof copy of A Stroll With William James by Jacques Barzun) (Box 257-259)
  - Adler, Mortimer J.:Paideia. Related materials & proof copies (Box 260)
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica materials, 1981 (Box 260)
  - Books & pamphlets relating to Jacques Barzun (Box 261)
  - Misc. correspondence, 1932-83 (Box 262)
  - Adler, Mortimer J.: The Paideia Proposal, 1983 (Box 262)
  - Appointment books-3 volumes, 1960-1973 (Box 262)
  - Awards-2 certificates, 1875-1980 (Box 262)
  - Modern American Usage. Introduction. Galley proofs (Box 262)
  - Music scores-2 a.ms. (Box 262)
  - The use & abuse of art. By J. Barzun. Xeroxed typescript, 1913-1983 (Box 262)
  - William James notes (correspondence, articles & references, manuscripts, photographs, and printed materials) (Box 263)
  - Printed misc. (Box 263)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun or with his notes (Box 264)
  - Books with Barzun's notes (Box 265)
  - Family correspondence (Box 2 boxes)
  - Poster (Box Oversize)
- Series XII: November 1984 Gift
  - Misc. correspondence, 1935-67 (Box 266)
  - Adler, Mortimer J.: The Paideia Proposal, 1978-84 (Box 266)
  - Advice to authors, 1981 (Box 266)
  - Advice to publishers, 1979-81 (Box 266)
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1981 (Box 267)
  - American Friends of Cambridge University, 1981-82 (Box 267)
  - Appointment books--2 vols., 1974-75 (Box 267)
  - Articles accepted, 1976-81 (Box 267)
  - Articles, Comments on, 1978-81 (Box 267)
  - Articles declined, 1976-81 (Box 267)
  - Columbia University -- Administrative, 1980-81 (Box 268)
  - Columbia University -- Personal, 1978-81 (Box 268)
  - Council tor Basic Education, 1981-82 (Box 268)
  - Council for Basic Education--History Commission, 1980-82 (Box 268)
  - Critic --Appeals, 1979-81 (Box 268)
  - Critic --General, 1976-82 (Box 268)
  - Educational criticism, 1979-81 (Box 268)
  - Encyc1opaedia Britannica, 1982-84 (Box 268)
  - Festschrift, Letters to contributors, 1977 (Box 269)
  - Interviews, 1961-80 (Box 269)
  - Lectures accepted, 1978-81 (Box 269)
  - Lectures Comments on, 1977-81 (Box 269)
  - Lectures declined, 1979-81 (Box 269)
  - Memberships & sponsorships, 1975-81 (Box 270)
  - Music, 1957-59 (Box 270)
  - Music--Harry Partch, 1948-57 (Box 270)
  - Outlines of his courses, 1956 & undated (Box 270)
  - Peabody Institute (Baltimore), 1982 (Box 270)
  - Permission requests, 1976-1979 (Box 270)
  - Publishing (articles & general correspondence), 1954-81 (Box 270)
  - Radio & TV programs, 1970-80 (Box 270)
  - Requests--misc., 1965-82 (Box 270)
  - Scribner's ---personal, 1976-84 (Box 271)
  - The University Col1ege at Buckingham, 1971-76 (Box 271)
  - Photocopies of manuscripts by others:
    - Caplow, Theodore (Box 271)
    - Jacobson, H.L. (Box 271)
  - Books by Barzun (correspondence, manuscripts and related materials):
    - Ber1ioz-articles &performances (Box 272)
    - Berlioz--sheets (Box 272)
    - Ber1ioz and His Century. (Box 272)
    - Berlioz and the Romantic Century. English edition. (Box 272)
    - Berlioz and the Romantic Century Third edition. (Box 272)
    - Berlioz:Evenings With the Orchestra. (Box 272)
    - Berlioz:New Letters of Berlioz, 1954-77 (Box 272)
    - Columbia History of the World, 1966-75 (Box 273)
    - Darwin Marx Wagner. (printed copy only) (Box 273)
    - The Modern Researcher, 1959-76 (Box 273)
    - Music in American Life, 1971-75 (Box 273)
    - Pleasures of Music, 1959-81 (Box 273)
    - A Rhetoric for Writers, 1968-75 (Box 273)
    - Teacher in America. (with a printed copy), 1944-83 (Box 273)
    - The Use and Abuse of Art. (with a printed copy in Japanese), 1971-74 (Box 273)
  - Royalty statements, arranged by publishers:
    - B-H (Box 274)
    - H-W (Box 275)
  - Books and periodicals with contributions by Barzun (Box 276)
  - Books inscribed to Barzun (Box 277)
- Series XIII: 1986-87 Gift
  - Correspondence: Students, 1972-83 (Box 278)
  - Advice to authors, 1982 (Box 279)
  - Advice to authors, 1983 (Box 279)
  - Advice to authors, 1984 (Box 279)
  - Advice to Publishers, 1985 (Box 279)
  - Advice to Publishers, 1980-July 86 (Box 280)
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts, 1981-86 (Box 280)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1981-86 (Box 280)
  - American Friends of Cambridge University, 1982-84 (Box 280)
  - American Illusions (Lecture Series), 1970 (Box 280)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1984-86 (Box 280)
  - The Armchair Detective (magazine), 1973-86 (Box 281)
  - Articles: Accepted, 1983-September 85 (Box 281)
  - Articles: Comments on (1), 1981-86 (Box 281)
  - Articles: Comments on (2), 1981-86 (Box 281)
  - Articles: Comments on "Behind the Blue Pencil", 1985-86 (Box 281)
  - Articles: Declined, 1982-September 85 (Box 282)
  - Articles: Possible, 1980-September 85 (Box 282)
  - Articles: Written, 1983 (Box 282)
  - Aspen Institute, 1983-85 (Box 282)
  - Author Guild, 1981-85 (Box 282)
  - Autographs from book flypapers, undated (Box 282)
  - Boston Athenaeum, 1975-85 (Box 282)
  - The Century Association, 1981-85 (Box 282)
  - Columbia University -- Administrative, 1982-83 (Box 282)
  - Columbia University Administrative, 1984-86 (Box 282)
  - Columbia University General correspondence, 1976-86 (Box 283)
  - Columbia University--Gifts (Box 283)
  - Columbia University Invitations (1), 1972-85 (Box 283)
  - Columbia University Invitations (2), 1977-86 (Box 283)